

🛘 (+47) 411 42 466 | 🗷 erik@i-solution.de | Rº Erik Kusch | 🕲 0000-0002-4984-7646 | 🌃 erikkusch.com | 🖫 ErikKusch | 💆 KuschErik

Research Profile

I am a biostatistican and data scientist specialised in streamlining work-flows as well as integrating and analysing heterogeneous data products. I use and develop quantitative tools to study the impacts of climate change and investigate the resilience of system at macro-scales to understand trajectories through time and space. My current work includes software development for climate data retrieval and aggregation as well as inference, analysis, and simulation of ecological networks.

Education

PhD in Biology; Specialisation on Ecoinformatics, Data Analysis and Biodiversity

01/2020 - 04/2023

AARHUS UNIVERSITY (AU) & OXFORD UNIVERSITY (OX)

A Macroecological Perspective to Ecological Networks - Exploring the Impacts of Climate-Driven Biodiversity Dissertation:

Change & Contrasting and Benchmarking Network Inference Approaches

M.Sc. in Biology; Specialisation on Biodiversity, Ecology and Evolution

08/2017 - 08/2019

University of Bergen (UiB) & Nansen Environmental and Remote Sensing Center (Nansen)

Thesis: Inferring Vegetation Memory From Remote Sensing Data And Identifying Causal Links To Plant Function

B.Sc. in Biology 10/2013 - 07/2017

TECHNICAL UNIVERSITY DRESDEN (TUD) & UNIVERSITY OF BERGEN (UIB)

Thesis: Remote Sensing And Predicting Shifts In Biome Distribution And Resilience Using NDVI Data

Specialised Training

Invasive Species Monitoring with Remote Sensing

NASA'S APPLIED REMOTE SENSING TRAINING (ARSET) 11/08/2024 - 28/08/2024

Open, Reproducible, and Transparent Science in Ecology Finse, Norway

University of Bergen 14/11/2022 - 18/11/2022

7th Edition Species Distribution Modelling Course Évora, Portugal

University of Évora, Science Retreats 26/04/2021 - 02/05/2021

An Introduction to Bayesian Statistics Glasgow, Scotland

University of Glasgow 06/04/2021 - 16/04/2021

Hierarchical Modelling of Species Communities with the R-package Hmsc Helsinki, Finland

02/11/2020 - 06/11/2020 University of Helsinki **Modelling Challenges for Mountain Ecosystems** Hamburg, Germany

University of Hamburg 23/02/2020 - 28/02/2020

Experience

Advisor Oslo, Norway

CICERO CENTER FOR INTERNATIONAL CLIMATE RESEARCH 09/2024 - PRESENT

Senior Engineer / Research Infrastructure Manager Oslo, Norway

NATURAL HISTORY MUSEUM, UNIVERSITY OF OSLO 03/2023 - 12/2024

Visiting Researcher Onna, Japan

OKINAWA INSTITUTE FOR SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY 02/2024 - 12/2024

Research Fellow Bergen, Norway

ECOLOGICAL AND ENVIRONMENTAL CHANGE RESEARCH GROUP, UNIVERSITY OF BERGEN 09/2019 - 12/2019

National Park Ranger & Environmental Education Guide Saxony, Germany

NATIONAL PARK SAXON-BOHEMIAN SWISS 04/2016 - 06/2016

Research and Teaching Assistant

BEHAVIOURAL ECOLOGY RESEARCH GROUP, UNIVERSITY OF LEIPZIG 08/2017 - 08/2019; 03/2017 - 04/2017

PRIMATE RESEARCH CENTRE, UNIVERSITY OF KYOTO 07/2018

GERMAN CENTRE FOR MARINE BIODIVERSITY RESEARCH, SENCKENBERG GROUP 05/2017 - 07/2017

NFDI4Biodiversity & iDiv Seasonal School on Data Management in Biodiversity and Environmental Science	© Course Material
Author & Lecturer	
Bayesian Networks Study Group	Personal Course Web Page
AUTHOR & LECTURER	•
AU Bayes Study Group	Personal Course Web Page
Author & Lecturer	
Excursions into Biostatistics	Course Web Page
Author & Lecturer	
An Introduction to Biostatistics Using R	② Course Web Page
Author & Lecturer	
Biological Research in Theory and Praxis (BFTP) AUTHOR	© Course Web Page Aarhus Universit
Teaching Assistant	Aarhus University
Applied Statistics	22/03/2021 - 14/05/202
STATISTICAL AND GEOSPATIAL MODELLING	03/09/2020 - 18/12/202
GEOSPATIAL INFORMATION SYSTEMS	27/10/2020 - 18/12/202
nstructor & Advisor	
ECOINFORMATICS & BIODIVERSITY MASTERS SEMINARS (EBMS), AARHUS UNIVERSITY	03/02/2021 - 05/05/202
Centre of Excellence in Biodiversity Education (BioCeed), University Of Bergen	08/2017 - 07/2018
Honours & Grants & Awards	
Scholarships & Grants	
 Scholarship for Academically Excellent Students, Frands Christian Frantsen's Scholars Funding for Particularly Talented Students, Lina Asbjørnsens Stipendiefond Fast-Track-Initiative Funding, FTI, Bjerknessenteret Project Grant, L. Meltzers Høyskolefond Scholarship, German Academic Scholarship Foundation (Studienstiftung des deutscher 	Bergen, Norwaj Bergen, Norwaj Bergen, Norwaj
Awards	
10/2019 Best Poster: Student and Early Career Researcher , International Society for Ecological 10/2019 Modeller's Choice Poster Award , International Society for Ecological Modelling	Modelling Salzburg, Austric Salzburg, Austric
Extracurricular Activity	
Group Leader	
Coders & Biostatisticians of NHM, University of Oslo	08/2023 - 12/202
NATURAL HISTORY MUSEUM COMPUTATIONAL BIOLOGY HELP-DESK, UNIVERSITY OF OSLO	08/2023 - 12/2024
Naturviterne Union Representative	
University of Oslo Natural History Museum	07/2023 - 12/202
Group Member	
STADIS – STABILITY AND DISCONTINUITY GROUP, UNIVERSITY OF OSLO	08/2023 - PRESEN
STATISTICS JOURNAL CLUB, UNIVERSITY OF GLASGOW	03/2021 - 03/202

03/2021 - 03/2023

09/2018 - 12/2019

12/2023 - PRESENT

05/2023 - 12/2024 03/2022 - 01/2023

SPATIAL SHARED-INTEREST GROUP, UNIVERSITY OF GLASGOW

University of Oslo Natural History Museum Dungeons & Dragons Group

AARHUS UNIVERSITY SECTION FOR ECOINFORMATICS DUNGEONS & DRAGONS GROUP

Bayes Study Group, University of Bergen

Leader & Dungeon MasterCICERO DUNGEONS & DRAGONS GROUP

Writing

Naturally formed canopy gaps increase tree species diversity in the tropical Moist Afromontane Forest of Gerba Dima, southwest Ethiopia

BEDILU TAFESSE, ERIK KUSCH, TAMRAT BEKELE, SEBESBE DEMISSEW, BIKILA WARKINEH, DESALEGN CHALA

A Yarnball of Frayed Strings - Communication, Impact & Cohesion of European Biodiversity Research Infrastructures

ERIK KUSCH, ALLAN T. SOUZA, YI-MING GAN, CARRIE ANDREW

Rx Preprint - 2024

TwinEco: A Unified Framework for Dynamic Data-Driven Digital Twins in Ecology

TAIMUR KHAN, KOEN DE KONING, DAG ENDRESEN, DESALEGN CHALA, ERIK KUSCH

Rx Preprint - 2024

Prototype biodiversity digital twin: crop wild relatives genetic resources for food security

DESALEGN CHALA, ERIK KUSCH, CLAUS WEILAND, CARRIE ANDREW, JONAS GRIEB, TUOMAS ROSSI, TOMAS MARTINOVIC, DAG ENDRESEN

Plant trait and vegetation data along a 1314 m elevation gradient with fire history in Puna grasslands, Perú

AUD HALBRITTER, VIGDIS VANDVIK, SEHOYA COTNER, [...], ERIK KUSCH, [...], BRIAN ENQUIST

Mature Scientific Data - 2024

A Novel Simulation Framework for Validation of Ecological Network Inference

ERIK KUSCH*, ANNA C. VINTON* (* ... JOINT FIRST-AUTHORSHIP)

Rx Preprint - 2023

Ecological Network Resilience & Extinction Proxies - Updating Projections of Ecological Networks

ERIK KUSCH, ALEJANDRO ORDONEZ

Rx Preprint - 2023

Ecological Network Inference is not Consistent Across Scales or Approaches

ERIK KUSCH, MALYON BIMLER, JAMES A. LUTZ, ALEJANDRO ORDONEZ

Rx Preprint - 2023

NetworkExtinction - R Package to Simulate Extinction Propagation & Rewiring Potential in Ecological Networks

 $\texttt{M.Isidora\, \'Avila-Thieme}^{\star}, \textbf{Erik\, Kusch}^{\star}, \texttt{Derek\, Corcoran}^{\star}, ..., \texttt{Navarrete}, \texttt{Pablo\, A.\, Marquet\, (}^{\star} ... \texttt{ Joint first-authorship)}$

Methods in Ecology and Evolution - 2023

MOSAIC: A Unified Trait Database to Complement Structured Population Models

Connor Bernard, Gabriel Silva Santos, [...], \mathbf{Erik} \mathbf{Kusch} , [...], $\mathbf{Roberto}$ Salguero-Gómez

• Nature Scientific Data - 2023

A novel trophic cascade between cougars and feral donkeys shapes desert wetlands

 ${\sf Erick \, Lundgren, \, Daniel \, Ramp, \, Owen \, Middleton, \, Eamonn \, Wooster, \, \textbf{Erik \, Kusch}, \, [...], \, Arian \, Wallach \, and \, and$

ᡂ Journal of Animal Ecology − 2022

Vegetation memory effects and their association with vegetation resilience in global drylands

ERIK KUSCH, RICHARD DAVY, ALISTAIR SEDDON

KrigR - A Tool for Downloading and Statistically Downscaling Climate Reanalysis Data

ERIK KUSCH, RICHARD DAVY

Environmental Research Letters - 2022

Reconciling high resolution climate datasets using KrigR

RICHARD DAVY, ERIK KUSCH

Environmental Research Letters - 2021